<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>King Iames his entertainment at Theobalds vvith his welcome to London, together with a salutatorie poeme. / By Iohn Sauile.</title>
            <author>Savile, John, poet.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21784</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116793</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852009</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852009</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17306</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11535)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17306)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1006:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>King Iames his entertainment at Theobalds vvith his welcome to London, together with a salutatorie poeme. / By Iohn Sauile.</title>
                  <author>Savile, John, poet.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Snodham, and are to be sould at the house of T. Este,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>KING IAMES his entertainment at Theobalds: With his welcome to London, <hi>together with a ſalutatorie Poeme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Sauile.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Dicito Iö paean, &amp; Iö bis dicito paean.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Snodham,</hi> and are to be ſould at the houſe of T. Eſte. 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:2"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull maſter <hi>George Sauile, ſonne and heire</hi> to Sir <hi>George Sauile knight, his moſt</hi> approued kinde patron; Health, honour, and happineſſe.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>OF ſpring of Gentrie, ſprig for honor dreſt,</l>
               <l>Tis half your loſſe (ô hel) but al my blame</l>
               <l>Jn proper words your worth ſhould not b'ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt,</l>
               <l>Let it ſuffice that I adore your name,</l>
               <l>Then pardon what is wanting, I will owe it,</l>
               <l>And as I'm able, J will pay I vow it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Meane while accept this poeme, to our King ſing</l>
               <l>Peruſe it at your leyſure, halfe or all,</l>
               <l>Your worſhips worth our Muſe ſhall ſhortly</l>
               <l>Though in true Poeſie, her skills but ſmall,</l>
               <l>How ere it be, accept her pure good will,</l>
               <l>She reſts at your command, in all <hi>Saue-ill.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips euer readie at command in all dutie, Iohn Sauile.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="description">
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:3"/>
            <head>King Iames his entertainement at <hi>Theobalds, with his welcome</hi> to London.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vrteous Reader, for the better vnderſtanding of this diſcription following, eſpecially to whom the ſcituation of the place is either leſſe knowne or not at all; they are therefore to note that <hi>Theobalds</hi> vvhether the Kings Mageſtie came vpon Tueſday, being the third of May, accompanied with his whole traine, is a Princely Mannor belonging to the right Honorable Sir <hi>Robert Cecill,</hi> principall Secretarie to his Mageſtie, and one of his Highnes Priuie Counſell, ſeated in the countie of Eſſex, twelue miles diſtant from London, directly by North, neere to an ancient towne called <hi>Walton-croſſe.</hi> This houſe is not placed adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the high way ſide, as manie ſumptuous buildings are in that countrie, and thereabouts, but eſpeciallie betweene that place and London, the moſt part whereof belong to the cittie Marchants; but hath a moſt ſtatelie walke, from the common ſtreet way whereby paſſengers trauaile vp to the Pallace, by the ſpace of one furlong in length, beſet about either ſide with yong Elme and Aſhe trees, confuſedly mixt one for another, from the high-way to the firſt court, belonging to the houſe, contayning in breadth three rods, which amount to ſome fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yards, in faſhion made like a high ridge land, or the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ſtreet way without biſhops gate. His Mageſtie hauing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:17306:4"/>vpon that ſame day with Sir <hi>Henrie Cocks</hi> at Broxburne, foure miles diſtant from Theobalds, about halfe an houre after one a clocke in the afternoone, his Highneſſe proceeded forward toward Theobalds, accompanied with Sir <hi>Edward Dennie</hi> then ſhriefe of Eſſex, hee had followers an hundred and fiftie in parti-coloured hats, red and yellow bands, round rould, with a feather in euerie one of them of the ſame colour, beſides two trumpeters all which were in blew coates gallantly moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. There did accompanie his Mageſtie from Broxburne, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the Nobilitie of England &amp; Scotland. As his Highneſſe was eſpied comming toward Theobalds, for very ioy many ran from their carts, leauing their teame of horſe to their owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable direction.</p>
            <p>After his approach nigh vnto Theobalds, the concourſe of people was ſo frequent, euery one more deſiring a ſight of him, that it were incredible to tell of. And it was wonderfull to ſee the infinit number of horſemen and footemen that went from the cittie of London that day thetherwards, and likewiſe from the counties of Kent, Surry, Eſſex, &amp; Middleſex, beſides many other countries: There were in my companie two more, who after I had put it into their mindes, what infinit numbers of horſe and foote paſſed by vs, after our breakfaſt at Edmunton, at the ſigne of the Bell, wee tooke occaſion to note how many would come downe in the next houre, ſo comming vp into a chamber next to the ſtreet, where wee might both beſt ſee and likewiſe take notice of all paſsingers, wee called for an houre-glaſſe, and after wee had diſpoſed of our ſelues who ſhould take the number of the horſe, and who the foote, wee turned the houreglaſſe, which before it was halfe runne out, we could not poſsiblie truelie number them, they came ſo exceedinglie faſt, but there wee broke off, and made our account of three hundred<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and nine horſe, and an hundred thirtie ſeauen foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which courſe continued that day from foure a clocke in the morning, till three a clocke after noone, and the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo, as the hoſt of the houſe told vs, without intermiſsion; now whether euerie equall ſpace did equall the number of
<pb facs="tcp:17306:4"/>theſe I cannot juſtly ſay, therefore I forbeare to ſet it downe. When we were come to Theobalds, wee vnderſtood his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtie to bee within the compaſſe of three quarters of a mile of the houſe, at which tidings wee deuided our ſelues into three parts, each one taking a place of ſpeciall note, to ſee what me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable accidents might happen within his compaſſe, one ſtanding at the vpper end of the walke, the ſecond at the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per end of the firſt court, the third at the ſecond court dore; and we had made choice of a gentleman of good ſort, to ſtand in the court that leads into the hall, to take notice what was done or ſaid by his highneſſe to the Nobilitie of our land, or ſaide or done by them to his Mageſtie, and to let vs vnderſtand of it, all which accidents as they hapned in their ſeuerall places, you ſhall heare in as few words as may be. Thus then for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſties comming vp the walke, ther came before his Mageſtie ſome of the Nobilitie, ſome Barons, Knights, Eſquires, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and others, amongſt whom was the Shriefe of Eſſex, and the moſt of his men, the trumpets ſounding next before his highneſſe, ſometimes one ſometimes another, his Mageſtie riding not continually betwixt the ſame two, but ſometimes one ſometimes another, as ſeemed beſt to his highneſſe, the whole Nobilitie of our land and Scotland round about him, obſeruing no place of ſuperiotie, all bare-headed, all whom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted from their horſes, at their entrance into the firſt court, ſaue onely his Mageſtie alone, who rid along ſtill, foure No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men laying their hands vpon his ſteed, two before and two behind, in this manner hee came, till hee was come to the court dore where my ſelfe ſtoode, where hee alighted from his horſe, from whom hee had not gone ten princely paces, but there was deliuered him a petition by a yong gentleman, his Mageſtie returning him this gracious anſwere, that he ſhould bee heard and haue juſtice.</p>
            <p>At the entrance into that court ſtood many noble men, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom was Sir <hi>Robert Cecil,</hi> who there meeting his Mageſtie conducted him into his houſe, all which was prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed with as great applauſe of the people as could bee, hartie
<pb facs="tcp:17306:5"/>prayer and throwing vp of hats. His Mageſtie had not ſtaied aboue an houre in his chamber, but hearing the multitude throng ſo faſt into the vppermoſt court to ſee his highneſſe, as his grace was informed, hee ſhewed himſelfe openly, out of his chamber window, by the ſpace of halfe an houre together, after which time hee went into the Laberinth-like garden to walke, where hee recreated himſelfe in the Meanders compact of Bayes, Roſemarie, and the like, ouerſhadowing his walke to defend him from the heate of the ſunne, till ſupper time, at which was ſuch plentie of prouiſion for all ſorts of men, in their due place as ſtruke mee with admiration, and firſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the ragged regiment, and ſuch as were debarred the priueledge of any court, theſe were ſo ſufficientlie rewarded with beefe, veale, mutton, bread and beere, that they ſung holli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day euery day, &amp; kept a continual feaſt; as for poore maimed &amp; diſtreſſed ſouldiers which repaired thether for maintenance, the wine, mony, and meat which they had in verie bounteous ſort, hath beene a ſufficient ſpur to cauſe them blaze it abroad ſince their comming to London, whoſe thankefulneſſe is not altogether vnknowne to my ſelfe, whom ſome of them hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that I was about to publiſh this ſmall remembrance, made meanes to mee to giue mee true information of ſuch princelie exhibition as they daily receiued, during the time of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſties aboade at Theobalds.</p>
            <p>But let vs a litle looke back, into the mirrour of Mageſtie, our ſoueraignes owne ſelfe, who in his princely wiſdome, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the multitude of people aſſembled together, had that prouident care ouer vs his louing ſubiects, foreſeeing that vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualls would be deere, both for horſe and man, had it bene per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to haue bene diſpoſed of, according to the inſatiable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the towne inhabitats, ratified a depoſition to that effect taken before the Clark of the market, for ſuch and ſuch vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualls, meale, bread, butter, egges, cheeſe, beefe, mutton, veale, &amp; the like, with lodging, and many moe ſuch neceſſarie matters, that they ſhould not be out of meaſure deare, beyond ordinary courſe and cuſtome, within the Verge of his Mageſties court,
<pb facs="tcp:17306:5"/>ſo long as it continued at Theobalds, what his princely inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was in this towards the publick good of all his faithfull ſubiects, then and there aſſembled together, meerely drawne with the bonds of loue and bounden dutie, may eaſily be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by the publication of the ſame, by his Mageſties priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; but how effectually this was obſerued by all eſtates of people, within the Verge of his Mageſties court, at the ſayd tyme, I referre it to the cenſure of them, that are aſſured of the certaintie of it.</p>
            <p>Vpon wedneſday morne, being the fourth of May, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtie rid very earely in the morning into Enfeeld chace, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with many of the nobilitie, his retourne was ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then was expected by a great deale, by reaſon the morning ſeemed to promiſe a ſhower, but did not performe it, I could haue wiſhed that either it had neuer lou'red at all, ſo we ſhould haue enioyed the preſence of his Mageſtie the longer, at that preſent, or elſe that the middle region would haue giuen vs iuſt cauſe to haue rayld againſt it, by vrging his highneſſe retourne into the houſe before his full recreation; he rid the moſt part of the way from the chace betwene two honourable perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of our land, the Earle of Northumberland vpon his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſties right hand, the Earle of Nothingham vpon his left ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Now one word concerning his Mageſties proceding towards London vpon ſatterday being the ſeauenth of May, and ſo wil end. For the number of people that went forth of the cittie of London to ſee his Mageſtie that day, doubtles they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in a number, but without all doubt not to be numbred. I heard many gray heads ſpeake it, that in all the meetings they haue ſeene or heard of, they neuer heard or ſaw the tenth man was there to be ſeene that day, betwixt Enfeeld and London, euerie place in this ſpace ſo clogd with companie, that his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe could not paſſe without pauſing, oft-times willingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, though more willing to haue proceeded, if conuenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he could without great perill to his beloued people. After our retourne to our houſes, in our recreating pratle, a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man then ſoiourning in my houſe, one maſter <hi>Th: Pa:</hi> a man
<pb facs="tcp:17306:6"/>vpon my owne knowledge of ſufficient wealth, yet he would haue bene content to haue exchanged his ſtate, ſo he might but haue had actually for euerie reaſonable creature was ther that day, a Bee, and a hiue to put them in. Another (more reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then he) would aske no more liuing, then for euerie one a pin, which according to an Arithmeticall proporcion, by the iudgement of two or three martiall men, who had ſeene great companies together, as neere as they could geſſe, by their ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſhow, would haue amounted to an hundred and fiftie pound, receaiuing but of euery one a pin. His Mageſtie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Stanford hill, ther was an oration made vnto his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the effect whereof I could not truely learne, and heare it I could not, by reaſon of the croud, for euen there being three miles from London, the people were ſo throng, that a ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>man let his cart for eight groats to eight perſons, whoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boad was not in it aboue one quarter of an houre. From Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford hill to London, was made a traine with a tame deare, with ſuch twinings and doubles, that the hounds could not take it faſter then, his Maieſtie proceeded, yet ſtill by the induſtrie of the huntſman, and the ſubtilitie of him that made the traine, in a full-mouthed crie all the way, neuer farther diſtant then one cloſe from the high way, whereby his highneſſe rid, and for the moſt part directly againſt his Mageſtie, whom together with the whole companie, had the lee winde from the hounds, to the end they might the better perceue and iudge of the vniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the crie. After his Mageſtie was come from Kings-land, there begun a diuiſion amongſt the people which way his Highneſſe would take when he came at Iſlington, but in fine, he came the higher way, by the weſt end of the Church, which ſtreet hath euer ſince, &amp; I geſſe euer wilbe called Kings ſtreet, by the enhabitants of the ſame. When his highnes had paſſed Iſlington and another place called New-rents, and entred into a cloſe called woods cloſe, by a way was cut of purpoſe through the banck, for his Mageſties more conuenient paſſage into the Charterhouſe garden, the people that were there aſſembled, I can compare to anothing more conueniently then to imagine
<pb facs="tcp:17306:6"/>euery graſſe to haue bene metamorphoſed into a man, in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the multitude was ſo maruelous, amongſt whome were the children of the hoſpital ſinging, orderly placed for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſties comming along through them, but all diſplaced, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the rudeneſſe of ſuch a multitude. After his Mageſtie was come amongſt the preſſe of the people, the ſhouts and clamours were ſo great, that one could ſcarce heare another ſpeake, and though there were no hope to finde what was loſt eſpecially by the looſer, notwithſtanding in token of exceſsiue ioy, inwardly conceaued in the hart, many threw vp their hats; Now at laſt he is entred into the garden, from which time till his going to the Tower, mine eies were neuer bleſt with his encounter. Now he is amongſt vs, God long preſerue him ouer vs, whoſe preſence makes old men ſing, <hi>Satis ſe vixiſſe ſe viſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:7"/>
            <head>A Salutatorie Poeme to the Mageſtie of King IAMES.</head>
            <l>HAile Mortall God, <hi>Englands</hi> true <hi>Ioy,</hi> great King,</l>
            <l>All haile, thy comming forceth my Muſe to ſing,</l>
            <l>Too forward, ſo vntutor'd in theſe laies,</l>
            <l>Vnfit to blazon Kings befitting praiſe,</l>
            <l>Yet neretheleſſe I'm forc'd perforce to write</l>
            <l>Some Furie doth my head my hand incite</l>
            <l>Antiquitie hath taught next that day</l>
            <l>That Engliſh harts firſt for your ſtate did pray,</l>
            <l>The Angell <hi>Gabriell,</hi> from <hi>Iehoua</hi> ſent,</l>
            <l>Told to the creature, what her maker ment,</l>
            <l>How ſhe a maiden wife ſhould beare a ſonne,</l>
            <l>Mankindes ſole Sauiour, when wee were vndone,</l>
            <l>This bleſſed eue of th'bleſt Annunciation,</l>
            <l>Was firſt day of your Highneſſe Proclamation</l>
            <l>What hopes, what haps this Proclamation brings</l>
            <l>Is cauſe efficient why our Muſes ſings.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:8"/>
            <l>Haile full of Grace: thus ginnes the ſalutation,</l>
            <l>Striking the bleſſed with deepeſt admiration,</l>
            <l>Halfe daunted firſt, then ſtraight no whit diſmaid</l>
            <l>Mildly made anſwere: <hi>Be't as my Lord hath ſaid,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Looke what ſurpaſsing ſolace, Ioy without meaſure</l>
            <l>Poſſeſt her ſoule for this caeleſtiall treaſure</l>
            <l>Entombing in her wombe our Sauiour deere</l>
            <l>Deign'd onely worthie, mans ſauing-health to beate,</l>
            <l>The like and more (if more or like could bee)</l>
            <l>Poſſeſt our ſoules, longing ſo long for thee.</l>
            <l>She bleſt the author of her good, the incarnate word</l>
            <l>Singing, <hi>My Soule doth magnifie my Lord,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>At tidings of your Proclamation wee</l>
            <l>In hands, in hats, in harts did all agree</l>
            <l>the world hath our applauſe, heauens haue our hartie praying,</l>
            <l>your ſelfe hands, hats, &amp; harts from you nere ſtraying.</l>
            <l>The fruit which came by th' Angels <hi>Aue</hi> t'all</l>
            <l>Is eaſely gathered by ould <hi>Adams</hi> fall,</l>
            <l>The world, the fleſh, the diuell, each one our foe,</l>
            <l>By <hi>Aue</hi> had their finall ouerthrow.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:8"/>
            <l>The fruit wee hope to reape, by God ſaue th'King,</l>
            <l>Which Englands counſell vnto the world did ring,</l>
            <l>'Pon that ſame dayes doubtleſſe beyond compare,</l>
            <l>Your ſelfe in Vertue, Learning, Valour rare.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Gabriell</hi> why ſtar'ſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Angell, why art thou ſlacke?</l>
            <l>Tell mee eternal meſſenger, what holds thee backe?</l>
            <l>To take thy wings leaue Demi-deitie,</l>
            <l>And bid God ſaue King <hi>Iames</hi> his Mageſtie,</l>
            <l>Sith thou'rt create to tell thy makers minde,</l>
            <l>And for no other end wert firſt aſsign'd.</l>
            <l>Old <hi>Homes</hi> writes a ſilly dogge could ſay</l>
            <l>Welcome to's maſter, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Perſius</hi> hath told vs, for great <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſake</l>
            <l>A ſpeechleſſe Parrate, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to's welcome ſpake,</l>
            <l>What ſhall our harts deuiſe? or hands ſet downe,</l>
            <l>Worthie thy great &amp; worthieſt King) renowne,</l>
            <l>But thouſand, of welcomes millions of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſend</l>
            <l>Plaudities numberleſſe, ſhouts wanting end,</l>
            <l>Should we not this doe, thankeleſſe were we then</l>
            <l>But oft it's ſeene, Beaſts are more kind then men.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:9"/>
            <l>Witneſſe old <hi>Bardus</hi> Ape, freed from the pit,</l>
            <l>That held a Senatour, and Snake within it,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Adrian</hi> promis'd <hi>Bardus</hi> halfe of all</l>
            <l>His goods, to rid him from his hunting fall.</l>
            <l>Poore man vntide his truſſe, let downe his rope,</l>
            <l>To pull out <hi>Adrian</hi> firſt, was all his hope,</l>
            <l>The Ape eſpying it, out of the priſon burſt,</l>
            <l>Clipping the line in's armes, was haild vp firſt,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Bardus</hi> lets downe his cord, the ſecond time,</l>
            <l>Entending <hi>Adrian,</hi> up therby ſhould clime,</l>
            <l>When 'twas come downe, neere to th'impriſoning ground,</l>
            <l>The Serpent cloſe himſelfe about it wound,</l>
            <l>He was releas'd the next, whom <hi>Bardus</hi> feing,</l>
            <l>Ran all agaſt, hoping t'eſcape by fleing,</l>
            <l>Laſtly the Senatour, faſt by it caught,</l>
            <l>Releaſed, neere thanked him for the deed he had wrought,</l>
            <l>Th'aforeſaid two wanting words, reaſon, arte,</l>
            <l>Did ſeuerall duties to him, in their heart.</l>
            <l>In thankfulneſſe, poore Ape did giue him wood,</l>
            <l>A precious ſtone for his receaued good.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:9"/>
            <l>The Serpent gaue him, thus we plainly ſee,</l>
            <l>For good receaued, thankfull dumb creatures bee.</l>
            <l>Why doe I inſtant in vngratefull man?</l>
            <l>Sith all are preſt to doe, ſay, ſhow; the beſt they can,</l>
            <l>To entertaine Englands vndoubted King,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Iames,</hi> firſt of that name, to his owne to bring,</l>
            <l>Doe not our Parrats <hi>Perſius</hi> aequall thine?</l>
            <l>When one mongſt many, ſo truelie could deuine,</l>
            <l>Could <hi>Augurize</hi> aright, foreſee, foreſay,</l>
            <l>A full month ſince, bidding King <hi>Iames</hi> good day,</l>
            <l>Vnſeene of moſt, hearing his onely name,</l>
            <l>Tel'ſt in the ſtreetes, reck'es not her teachers blame,</l>
            <l>Naming him twentie tymes at leaſt together,</l>
            <l>Ceaſing no longer, than oyling of a feather,</l>
            <l>Twixt each King <hi>Iames,</hi> or King, or good, or day,</l>
            <l>And oft poore foole, ſhe totally will pray,</l>
            <l>Withouten ceaſing, vtter the whole throughout</l>
            <l>To th' admiration, of the gazing rout.</l>
            <l>I cannot deeme it now gulling toye,</l>
            <l>Which <hi>Vennard</hi> inſpir'd) intituled <hi>Englands Ioye.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:10"/>
            <l>I rather geſſe hee did our good diuine</l>
            <l>Not daring to diſcloſ't before full time,</l>
            <l>Be bold, goe on, nowe's thy praeſaging plaine,</l>
            <l>King <hi>Iames</hi> is <hi>Englands ioy,</hi> long hop'd for gaine,</l>
            <l>That it is hee, who cannot eaſely proue?</l>
            <l>Sith it is onely hee, wee onely loue,</l>
            <l>Tis hee that <hi>Englands ioy</hi> did firſt awake,</l>
            <l>After ſad ſorrowing for <hi>Elizaes</hi> ſake,</l>
            <l>Then reck no clowniſh trumps, regard them naught,</l>
            <l>Baniſh ſuch <hi>Fooleries</hi> from thy purer thought,</l>
            <l>Wee know the fruit, ſprung from foreknowing pen,</l>
            <l>King <hi>Iames</hi> is <hi>Englands ioy,</hi> ſay all Amen.</l>
            <l>Tokens of <hi>Englands ioy</hi> who liſt to ſeeke,</l>
            <l>that night might find them ſtraw'd in London ſtreet,</l>
            <l>Making the night a day, <hi>Phoebe</hi> a Sunne,</l>
            <l>This was the firſt ſigne when our <hi>Ioy</hi> begun,</l>
            <l>Continu'd ſtill t' Englands aeternall good</l>
            <l>In th'happie iſſue of your Royall blood,</l>
            <l>Make haſt to make vs happie (worthie King)</l>
            <l>Our Muſe deſires to write th'inthr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>izing</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:10"/>
            <l>At famous Weſtminſter, in thy elders chaire,</l>
            <l>Where Englands peeres, will yeeld our Crowne to th'heir</l>
            <l>To th'heire legitimate, your ſelfe dread Soueraigne,</l>
            <l>Wiſhing your happie and victorious Raigne.</l>
            <l>Beſids a trine of Kingdomes, are your owne,</l>
            <l>Poſſeſſe them all, poſſeſſing Englands Crowne,</l>
            <l>Fraunce and froward Ireland, with our Engliſh land,</l>
            <l>Are feall ſubiects to your Regall hand.</l>
            <l>Beſides your ſacred ſelfe, doth bring with you,</l>
            <l>A Kingdome neuer knit to theſe till now,</l>
            <l>As <hi>Camdens Brittaine</hi> tells, ſince <hi>Brutus</hi> daies,</l>
            <l>Than let vs thank our God, ſing Roundelaies,</l>
            <l>England reioyce, Saint <hi>George</hi> for England ſhout,</l>
            <l>For ioy Saint <hi>Denis</hi> crie, all Fraunce throughout.</l>
            <l>Double thy ioyes ô <hi>Albion</hi> harke <hi>Cambrian</hi> banks,</l>
            <l>God hath enrich'd thee with a Prince, giue hartie tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks</l>
            <l>You that of long, had Lords in judgement ſit,</l>
            <l>Deciding cauſes, for your countrie ſit.</l>
            <l>Clap hands, ſing <hi>Io,</hi> chaungd is your gouernment,</l>
            <l>Our Kings deareſt ſonn's, your Prince, your Preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:11"/>
            <l>Saint <hi>Dauid</hi> ring, for ioy ſet vp your leeke,</l>
            <l>Your praier's heard, you haue got, you long did ſeeke</l>
            <l>Braue <hi>Henrie Fredericke,</hi> that Imperiall name,</l>
            <l>I geſſe from his Natiuitie foretold the ſame,</l>
            <l>Thrice happie in his threefold name are you,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Henrie</hi> bould <hi>Fredericke</hi> is a <hi>Steward</hi> true,</l>
            <l>How well theſe titles with your names agree?</l>
            <l>You almoſt all (at leaſt poſſeſſing) three,</l>
            <l>Welcome then hartely, welcom braue Prince <hi>Henrie,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Sing Carrols for his ſake, keepe wakes, bee merrie,</l>
            <l>Irefull cold <hi>Ireland,</hi> ceaſe from thy rage at laſt,</l>
            <l>To yeeld ſubjection to thy King make haſt,</l>
            <l>Sound out Saint <hi>Patricke,</hi> Scotland Saint <hi>Andrew</hi> ſing</l>
            <l>King <hi>Iames</hi> is Englands, Scotlands, Fraunce, Irelands King,</l>
            <l>What can I add to eeke our ioyes withall,</l>
            <l>Sith <hi>Iames</hi> is King of all, contain'd in all,</l>
            <l>But haſt deere King, t'caſe our expecting minde,</l>
            <l>Vnſtaied while your Highneſſe ſtaies behinde,</l>
            <l>Indeede nere truelie ſtaied, till wee you greete,</l>
            <l>With <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in London ſtreet.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:11"/>
            <l>Nor then indeede, till wee doe all reſort</l>
            <l>To ſee your face ſhining in Englands Court,</l>
            <l>And then (ô but till then make haſt) your grace ſhall ſee</l>
            <l>Your ſtranger ſubiects faithfull loyaltie.</l>
            <l>Now to returne where firſt I did beginne,</l>
            <l>Mongſt all eſtates Poets haue cauſe to ſing</l>
            <l>King <hi>Iames</hi> his welcome; for hee doth excell</l>
            <l>As his <hi>Lepantho</hi> and his <hi>Furies</hi> tell</l>
            <l>In Poeſie: all Kings in Chriſtendome,</l>
            <l>Then welcome him (quick ſpirits) bluſh to be dumbe</l>
            <l>And pardon him that boldlie makes this ſuite</l>
            <l>Forc'd by ſome Furie, ſcornes to bee longer mute,</l>
            <l>Reioyce your Patron is your countries King,</l>
            <l>Iudge; of all ſtates, haue not you cauſe to ſing?</l>
            <l>For ſhame then rouſe your ſpirits, awake for ſhame,</l>
            <l>Giue <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s due, acquit your ſelues from blame,</l>
            <l>All wiſh his welcome, mongſt all ſorts of men,</l>
            <l>Saue onelie ſuch as are paſt ſixtie ten,</l>
            <l>Theſe wayward old ones grudge to leaue behind</l>
            <l>What our ſucceeding age is ſure to finde.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:12"/>
            <l>The peace, the plentie, pleaſure, and ſuch like gaine,</l>
            <l>Which we are ſure t'enioy in <hi>Iames</hi> his raigne.</l>
            <l>Wiſhing would he had liu'd in their youths prime,</l>
            <l>Or old-age would returne to ten and nyne,</l>
            <l>Were they but nynteene, who haue nyntie ſeene.</l>
            <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would they wiſh to ſee king <hi>Iames</hi> and's Queene,</l>
            <l>And ſo indeed they doe, the whiteſt heads</l>
            <l>That liu'd in Antique tyme, and praid on beades,</l>
            <l>Theſe holieſt fathers craue no longer lyfe,</l>
            <l>Then once to ſee King <hi>Iames,</hi> his Queene and wyfe.</l>
            <l>With hands vprear'd, giuing <hi>IEHOVAH</hi> praiſe,</l>
            <l>That lenght their liues, to ſee his happie daies,</l>
            <l>That theſe his happie daies, full grace may bring,</l>
            <l>Let Engliſh hearts crie all, God laue our King.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17306:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
